<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: vim | Notes to Self]]></title>
  <link href="http://ciwchris.github.com/blog/categories/vim/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ciwchris.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-02-16T12:32:42-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://ciwchris.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Chris]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Entering escape in insert mode]]></title>
    <link href="http://ciwchris.github.com/blog/2013/02/16/entering-escape-in-insert-mode/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-16T16:17:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://ciwchris.github.com/blog/2013/02/16/entering-escape-in-insert-mode</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the previous post I created a macro which made use of an 'escape':</p>

<p><code>vim
^dwA ^[pxj
</code>
When outputting the contents of the register containing this macro the 'escape' is translated as <code>^[</code>. This shouldn't be surpising. This format is known as <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caret_notation">caret notation</a> and is used to represent non-printable control characters in ASCII. That explains the caret, but why the bracket? Interestingly, the bracket, by default, can be used as an alternative to the 'escape' key in Vim, <code>h: i-ctrl-[</code>. The reason for the bracket has to do with <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Control_character#How_control_characters_map_to_keyboards">how control characters are mapped on keyboards</a>. As stated in the article, control characters are rendered by the ASCII value of the non-printable character plus 64. In this case the 'escape' key has the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ASCII#ASCII_control_characters">ASCII value of 27</a>. Adding 64 to this value gives us the decimal value of 91, which is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ASCII#ASCII_printable_characters">represented by the bracket, '['</a>. And that is why the 'escape' was rendered as <code>^[</code> in the macro. <code>h: key-notation</code> contains a table detailing how many non-printable characters can be rendered in Vim.</p>

<p>The follow up question to this would be, "if I were to create the macro myself how would I type <code>^[</code>?" If the caret key was literally used then it would instruct Vim to move to the "first non-blank character of the line", <code>:h ^</code>. Not our desired outcome. To type an 'escape' it is necessary to use 'ctrl-v', which will "insert next non-digit literally", <code>:h i_ctrl-v</code>. So to use an 'escape' in a macro being created manually type: 'ctrl-v' followed by 'escape'.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[examining the contents of a macro]]></title>
    <link href="http://ciwchris.github.com/blog/2013/02/13/examining-the-contents-of-a-macro/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-13T15:42:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://ciwchris.github.com/blog/2013/02/13/examining-the-contents-of-a-macro</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Macros are a breeze in Vim! But often I make a mistake while recording the macro, undo my change and repeat. Hopefully I get it right the next time, but I'd rather not look at the statistics. It turns out the registers Vim stores macros in are the same set of registers used for other operations. What this means is that I can <code>put</code> the contents of the register, modify it and then <code>yank</code> it back in. Let's say I had the following list of names:</p>

<p><code>
John Smith
Joe Smith
Bob Smith
Mike Smith
Juan Carlos
Jane Smith
Mike Jones
David Smith
Sarah Smith
James Smith
</code>
And I want to swap the first name and last name. There are many ways to do this but using a macro one may write:</p>

<p><code>vim
^dwA ^[pxj
</code></p>

<p>I can read these commands into register <code>a</code> by yanking the line like so, <code>"ay$</code>. Now I can use it as a macro to swap the names, <code>10@a</code>. Voilà!</p>

<p><code>
Smith John
Smith Joe
Smith Bob
Smith Mike
Carlos Juan
Smith Jane
Jones Mike
Smith David
Smith Sarah
Smith James
</code></p>

<p>To always make this macro avaiable I can save it in my <code>.vimrc</code>.</p>

<p><code>vim
let @a='^dwA ^[pxj'
</code></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reversing a file in vim]]></title>
    <link href="http://ciwchris.github.com/blog/2013/02/11/reversing-a-file-in-vim/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-11T14:30:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://ciwchris.github.com/blog/2013/02/11/reversing-a-file-in-vim</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Digging through the Vim help docs <code>:h usr_12.txt</code> I came across the topic 'Reverse line order', <code>h 12.1</code>. Sounds interesting. The command is:</p>

<p><code>vim
:global/^/m 0
</code>
While familar with <code>:global</code> the rest of the command was mysterious. The documentation did a good job breaking this down. <code>^</code> will match the beginning of every line. <code>m 0</code> will <code>:move</code> the line below the line number specified; in other words move the current line to the first line of the file. Line '0' is called the 'mythical zeroth line', according to the docs. The same came be done with a range using marks:</p>

<p>``` vim
:'t+1,.g/<sup>/m</sup> 't
````
Here, assuming mark 't' has been set, then all lines between it and the current line will be reversed.</p>

<p><code>:move</code> was also new to me, although straight forward. It's compliment, <code>:copy</code>, it also worth noting here, also defined as <code>:t</code>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
